hey everyone welcome to the ninth and
final lecture of full stack deep
learning 2022. today we'll be talking
about ethics after going through a
little bit of context of what it is that
we mean by ethics what I mean by ethics
when I talk about it we'll go through
three different areas where ethics comes
up both Broad tech ethics ethics that
anybody who works in the tech industry
broadly needs to think about and care
about what ethics has meant specifically
for the machine learning industry what's
happened in the last couple of years as
ethical concerns have come to the
Forefront and then finally what ethics
might mean in a future where true
artificial general intelligence exists
so first let's do a little bit of
context setting even more so than other
topics all lectures on ethics are wrong
but some of them are useful and they're
more useful if we admit and state what
our assumptions or biases or approaches
are before we dive into the material and
then I'll also talk about three kind of
General themes that I see coming up
again and again when ethical concerns
are raised in Tech and in machine
learning themes of alignment themes of
trade-off and the critical theme of
humility so in this lecture I'm going to
approach ethics on the basis of concrete
cases specific instances where people
have raised concerns so we'll talk about
cases where people have taken actions
that have led to claims and counter
claims of ethical or unethical Behavior
the use of automated weapons the use of
machine learning systems for making
decisions like sentencing and bail and
the use of machine learning algorithms
to generate art in each case one
criticism has been raised part of the
criticism has been that the technology
Awards impact is unethical so
approaching ethics in this way allows me
to give my favorite answer to the
question of what is ethics which is to
quote one of my favorite philosophers
Ludwig wickenstein and say that the
meaning of a word is its use in the
language so we'll be focusing on times
when people have used the word ethics to
describe what they like or dislike about
some piece of technology and this
approach to definition is an interesting
one if you want to try it out for
yourself you should check out the game
something something soup something which
is a browser game at the link in the
bottom left of this slide in which you
presented with a bunch of dishes and you
have to decide whether they are soup or
not soup whether they can be served to
somebody who ordered soup and by playing
a game like this you can discover both
how difficult it is to really put your
finger on a concrete definition of soup
and how poorly maybe your working
definition of soup fits with any given
soup theory because of this sort of
case-based approach we won't be talking
about ethical schools and we won't be
doing any trolley problems so this
article here from current affairs asks
you to consider this particular example
of a of an ethical dilemma where an
asteroid containing all of the
universe's top doctors who are working
on a cure for all possible illnesses is
hurtling towards the planet of Orphans
and you can destroy the asteroid and
save the orphans but if you do so the
hope for a cure for all diseases will be
lost forever and the question posed by
the authors of this article is is this
hypothetical useful at all for
Illuminating any moral truths so rather
than considering these hypothetical
scenarios about trolley cars going down
rails and fat men standing on Bridges
we'll talk about concrete specific
examples from the last 10 years of work
in our field and adjacent Fields but
this isn't the only way of talking about
or thinking about ethics it's the way
that I think about it is the way that I
prefer to talk about it is not the only
one and it might not be the one that
works for you so if you want another
point of view and one that really
emphasizes and loves trolley problems
then you should check out sergey's
lecture from the last edition of the
course from 2021 it's a really
delightful talk and presents some
similar ideas from a very different
perspective coming to some of the same
conclusions and some different
conclusions a useful theme team from
that lecture that I think we should all
have in mind when we're pondering
ethical dilemmas and the related
questions that they bring up is the
theme of what is water from last year's
lecture so this is a famous little story
from a commencement speech by David
Foster Wallace where an older fish swing
by two younger fish says morning boys
how's the water and after he swims away
one of the younger fish turns the other
and says wait what the hell is water the
idea is that if we aren't thoughtful if
we aren't paying attention some things
that are very important can become
background can become assumption and can
become invisible and so when I share
these slides with Sergey he challenged
me to answer this question for myself
about how we were approaching ethics
this time around and I'll say that this
approach of relying on prominent cases
risks replicating a lot of social biases
some people's ethical claims are
Amplified and some fall on unhearing
ears some stories travel more because
the people involved have more resources
and are better connected and using these
forms of case-based reasoning where you
explain your response or your beliefs in
terms of these concrete specifics can
end up hiding the principles that are
actually in operation maybe you don't
even realize that that's how you're
making the decision maybe some of the
true ethical principles that you're
operating under can disappear like water
to these fish so don't claim that the
approach I'm taking here is perfect but
in the end so much of Ethics is deeply
personal that we can't expect to have a
perfect approach we can just do the best
we can and hopefully better every day so
we're gonna see three themes repeatedly
come up throughout this talk two
different forms of conflict that give
rise to ethical disputes one when there
is conflict between what we want and
what we get and another when there is
conflict between what we want and what
others want and then finally a theme of
maybe an appropriate response a response
of humility when we don't know what we
want or how to get it the problem of
alignment where what we want and what we
get differ we'll come up over and over
again and one of the primary drivers of
this is what you might call the proxy
problem which is in the end we are often
optimizing or maximizing some proxy of
the thing that we really care about and
if the alignment or Loosely the
correlation between that proxy and the
thing that we actually care about is
poor enough then by trying to maximize
that proxy we can end up hurting the
thing that we originally cared about
there is a nice paper that came out just
very recently doing a mathematical
analysis of this idea that's actually
been around for quite some time excuse
you can see these kinds of proxy
problems everywhere once you're looking
for them on the top right I have a train
and validation loss chart from one of
the training runs for the full stack
deep learning text recognizer the thing
that we can actually optimize is the
training loss that's what we can use to
calculate gradients and improve the
parameters of our network but the thing
that we really care about is the
performance of the network on data
points it hasn't seen like the
validation set or the test set or data
in production if we optimize our
training lost too much then we can
actually cause our validation loss to go
up similarly there was an interesting
paper that suggested that increasing
your accuracy on classification tasks
can actually result in a decrease in the
utility of your embeddings in Downstream
tasks and you can find these proxy
problems outside of machine learning as
well there's a famous story involving a
Soviet Factory and nails that turned out
to be false but in looking up a
reference for it I was able to find an
actual example where a factory that was
making chemical machines rather than
creating a machine that was cheaper and
better chose not to adopt producing that
machine because their output was
measured in weight so the thing that
that the planners actually cared about
economic efficiency and output was not
what was being optimized for because it
was too difficult to measure and one
reason why these kinds of proxy problems
arise so frequently is due to issues of
information the information that we're
able to measure is not the information
that we want so the training loss is the
information that we have but the
information that we want is the
validation loss but then at a higher
level we often don't even know what it
is that we truly need so we may want the
validation loss but what we need is the
loss in production or really the value
our users will derive from this model
but even when we do know what it is that
we want or what it is that we need we're
likely to run into the second kind of
problem the problem of a trade-off
between stakeholders going back to our
hypothetical example with the asteroid
of doctors hurtling towards the planet
of Orphans what makes this challenging
is the need to determine a trade-off
between the wants and needs of the
people on the asteroid the wants and
needs of the orphans on the planet and
the wants and needs of future people who
cannot be reached for comment and to
weigh in on this concern is some
sometimes said that this need to
negotiate trade offices one of the
reasons why Engineers don't like
thinking about some of these problems
around ethics I don't think that's quite
right because we do accept trade-offs as
a key component of engineering there's
this nice O'Reilly book on the
fundamentals of software architecture
the first thing that they State at the
very beginning is that everything in
software architecture is a trade-off and
even this satirical oh really book says
that every programming question has the
answer it depends so we're comfortable
negotiating trade-offs take for example
this famous chart comparing the
different convolutional networks on the
basis of their accuracy and the number
of operations that it takes to run them
thinking about these kinds of trade-offs
between speed and correctness is exactly
the sort of thing that we have to do all
the time in our job as engineers and one
part of it that is maybe easier is at
least selecting What's called the Pareto
front for the metrics that we care about
my favorite way of remembering what a
Pareto front is is this definition of a
data scientist from Josh Wills which is
a data scientist who's better at Stats
than any software engineer and better at
software engineering than any
statistician so this Pareto front that
I've drawn here is the models that have
are more accurate than anybody who takes
fewer flops and use fewer flops than
anybody who is more accurate so I think
rather than fundamentally being about
trade-offs one of the reasons why
Engineers maybe dislike thinking about
these problems is that it's really hard
to identify the axes for a chart like
the one that I just showed it's very
hard to quantify these things and if we
do quantify things like the utility or
the rights of people involved in a
problem we know that those
quantifications are far away from what
what they truly want to measure there's
a proxy problem in fact but even further
ones measured where on that front do we
fall as Engineers we maybe develop an
expertise in knowing whether we want
high accuracy or low latency or
computational load but we are not as
comfortable deciding how many current
orphans we want to trade for what amount
of future health so this raises
questions both in terms of measurement
and in terms of decision making that are
outside of our expertise so the
appropriate response here is humility
because we don't explicitly train these
skills the way that we do many of the
other skills that are critical for our
job and many folks engineers and
managers in technology seem to kind of
deepen their bones prefer optimizing
single metrics making a number go up so
there's no trade-offs to think about and
those metrics are they're not proxies
they're the exact same thing that you
care about my goal within this company
my objective for this quarter my North
Star is user growth or lines of code and
by God I'll make that go up so when we
encounter a different kind of problem
it's important to bring a humble mindset
a student mindset to the problems to ask
for help to look for experts and to
recognize that the help that you get and
the experts that you find might not be
immediately obviously which you want or
what you're used to additionally one
form of this that we'll see repeatedly
is that when attempting to intervene
because of an ethical concern it's
important to remember this same humility
it's easy to think when you are on the
good side that this humility is not
necessary but even trying to be helpful
is a delicate and dangerous undertaking
one of my favorite quotes from the
systems Bible so we want to make sure as
we resolve the ethical concerns that
people raise about our technology that
we come up with solutions that are not
just part of the problem so the way that
I resolve all of these is through user
orientation by getting feedback from
users we maintain alignment between
ourselves and the system that we're
creating and the users that it's meant
to serve and then when it's time to make
trade-offs we should resolve them in
consultation with users and in my
opinion we should tilt the scales in
their favor and away from the favor of
other stakeholders including within our
own organization and then humility is
one of the reasons why we actually
listen to users at all all because we
are humble enough to recognize that we
don't have the answers to all of these
questions all right with our context and
our themes under our belt let's dive
into some concrete cases and responses
we'll start by considering ethics in the
broader world of technology that machine
learning fights itself in so the key
thing that I want folks to take away
from this section is that the tech
industry cannot afford to ignore ethics
as public trust in Tech declines we need
to learn from other nearby industries
that have done a better job on
professional ethics and then we'll talk
about some contemporary topics some that
I find particularly interesting and
important throughout the past decade the
technology industry has been plagued by
Scandal whether that's how technology
companies interface with national
governments at the largest scale over to
how technological systems are being used
or manipulated by people creating
disinformation or fake social media
accounts or targeting children with
automatically generated content that
hacks the YouTube recommendation system
and the impact effect of this has been
that distrust in tech companies has
risen markedly in the last 10 years so
this is from the public affairs pulse
survey just last year the tech industry
went from being in 2013 one of the
industries that the fewest people felt
was less trustworthy than average to
rubbing elbows with famously much
distrusted Industries like energy and
pharmaceuticals and the tech industry
doesn't have to win elections so we
don't have to care about public polling
as much as politicians but politicians
care quite a bit about those public
opinion polls and just in the last few
years the fraction of people who believe
that the large tech companies should be
more regulated has gone up a substantial
amount and comparing it to 10 years ago
it's astronomically higher so there will
be substantial impacts on our industry
due to this loss of public trust so as
machine learning engineers and
researchers we can learn from nearby
Fields so I'll talk about two of them
one a nice little bit about the culture
of professional ethics in Engineering in
Canada and then a little bit about
ethical standards for human subjects
research so one of the worst
construction disasters in modern history
was the collapse of the Quebec bridge in
1907. 75 people who were working on the
bridge at the time were killed and a
parliamentary inquiry placed the blame
pretty much entirely on two engineers in
response there was the development of
some additional rituals that many
Canadian Engineers take part in when
they finish their education that are
meant to impress upon them the weight of
their responsibility so one component of
this is a large iron ring which
literally impresses that weight upon
people and then another is an oath that
people take a non-legally binding oath
that includes saying that I will not
hence forward suffer or pass or be privy
to the passing of bad workmanship or
faulty material I think the software
would look quite a bit different if
software Engineers took an oath like
this and took it seriously one other
piece I wanted to point out is that it
includes within it some built-in
humility asking pardon ahead of time for
the assured failures lots of machine
learning is still in the research stage
and so some people may say that oh well
that's important for the people who are
building stuff but I'm working on R D
for fundamental technology so I don't
have to worry about that but research is
also subject to regulation so this is
something I was required to learn
because I did my PhD in a neuroscience
Department that was funded by the
National Institutes of Health which
mandates training in ethics and in the
ethical conduct of research so these
regulations for human subjects research
date back to the 1940s when there were
medical experiments on unwilling human
subjects by totalitarian regimes this is
still pretty much the Cornerstone for
laws on human subjects research around
the world through the Helsinki
declaration which gets regularly updated
in the US the Touchstone bit of
regulation on this the 9 1973 research
act requires among other things informed
consent from people who are
participating in research and there were
two major revelations in the late 60s
and early 70s that led to this
legislation not dissimilar to the
scandals that have plagued the
technology industry recently one was the
infliction of hepatitis on mentally
disabled children in New York in order
to test hepatitis treatments and the
other was the non-treatment of syphilis
in black men at Tuskegee in order to
study the progression of the disease in
both cases these subjects did not
provide informed consent and seemed to
be selected for being unable to advocate
for themselves or to get legal redress
for the harms they were suffering and so
if we are running experiments and those
experiments involve humans evolve our
users we are expected to adhere to the
same principles and one of the famous
instances of mismatch between the
culture in our industry and the culture
of human subjects research was was when
some researchers at Facebook studied
emotional contagion by altering people's
news feeds either adding more negative
content or adding more positive content
and they found a modest but robust
effect that introducing more positive
content caused people to post more
positively when people found out about
this they were very upset the authors
noted that Facebook's data use policy
includes that the user's data and
interactions can be used for this but
most people who were Facebook users and
the editorial board of pnas where this
was published did not see it that way so
put together I think we are at the point
where we need a professional code of
ethics for software hopefully many codes
of Ethics developed in different
communities that can Bubble Up compete
with each other and merge to finally
something that most of us or all of us
can agree on and that is incorporated
into our education and acculturation of
new members into our field and into more
aspects of how we build to close out
this section I wanted to talk about some
particular ethical concerns that arise
in Tech in general first around carbon
emissions and then second around dark
patterns and user hostile designs the
good news with carbon emissions is that
because they scale with cost it's only
something that you need to worry about
when the costs of what you're building
what you're working on are very large at
which time you both won't be alone in
making these decisions and you can move
a bit more deliberately and make these
choices more thoughtfully so first what
are the ethical concerns with carbon
emissions anthropogenic climate change
driven by CO2 emissions raises a classic
trade-off which was dramatized in this
episode of Harvey Birdman Attorney at
Law in which George Jetson travels back
from the future to sue the present for
melting the ice caps and destroying his
civilization so unfortunately we don't
have future Generations present now to
advocate for themselves the other view
is that this is an issue that arises
from a classic alignment problem which
is many organizations are trying to
maximize their profit that raw profit is
based off of prices for goods that don't
include externalities like the
environmental damage caused by carbon
dioxide emissions leading to increased
temperatures and climactic change so the
primary Dimension along which we have to
worry about carbon emissions is in
compute jobs that require power that
power has to be generated somehow and
that can result in the emission of
carbon and so there was a nice paper
Linked In This slide that walked through
how much carbon dioxide was emitted
using typical us-based Cloud
infrastructure and the top headline from
this paper was that training a large
Transformer model with neural
architecture search produces as much
carbon dioxide as five cars create
during their lifetime so that sounds
like quite a bit of carbon dioxide and
it is in fact but it's important to
remember that power is not free and so
there is a metric that we're quite used
to tracking that is at least correlated
with our carbon emissions our compute
spend and if you look for the cost runs
between one and three million dollars to
run the neural architecture search that
emitted five cars worth of CO2 and one
to three million dollars is actually a
bit more than it would cost to buy five
cars and provide their fuel so the
number that I like to use is that four
us-based Cloud infrastructure like the
US West one that many of us find
ourselves in ten dollars of cloud spend
is roughly equal to one dollar worth of
air travel costs so that's on the basis
of something like the numbers in the
chart indicating air travel across the
United States from New York to San
Francisco I've been taking care to
always say us-based cloud infrastructure
because just changing Cloud regions can
actually reduce your emissions quite a
bit there's actually a factor of nearly
50x from some of the some of the cloud
regions that have have the most carbon
intensive power generation like AP
Southeast 2 and the regions that have
the the least carbon intensive power
like ca Central one that chart comes
from a nice talk from hugging face that
you can find on YouTube part of their
course that talks a little bit more
about that paper and about managing
carbon emissions interest in this
problem has led to some nice new tooling
one code carbon dot IO allows you to
track power consumption and therefore
CO2 emissions just like you would any of
your other metrics and then there's also
this mlco2 impact tool that's oriented a
little bit more directly towards machine
learning the other ethical concern in
Tech that I wanted to bring up is
deceptive design and how to recognize it
an unfortunate amount of deception is
tolerated in some areas of software the
example on the left comes from an
article by Narayanan at all that shows a
fake countdown timer that claims that an
offer will only be available for an hour
but when it hits zero nothing the offer
is still there there's also a possibly
apocryphal example on the right here you
may have seen these numbers next to
products when online shopping saying
that some number of people are currently
looking at this product this little
snippet of JavaScript here produces a
random number to put in that spot so
that example on the right may not be
real but because of real examples like
the one on the left it strikes a chord
with a lot of developers and Engineers
there's a kind of slippery slope here
that goes from being unclear or maybe
not maximally upfront about something
that is a source of friction or a
negative user experience in your product
and then in trying to remove that
friction or sand that edge down you
slowly find yourself being effectively
deceptive to your users on the left is a
nearly complete history of the way
Google displays ads in its search engine
results it started off very clearly
colored and separated out with a bright
color from the rest of the results and
then a about 10 years ago that colored
background was removed and replaced with
just a tiny little colored snippet that
said add and now as of 2020 that small
bit there is no longer even colored it's
just bolded and so this makes it
difficult for users to know which
content is being served to them because
somebody paid for them to see it versus
being served up organically so a number
of patterns of deceptive design also
known as dark patterns have emerged over
the last 10 years you can read about
them on this website deceptive.design
there's also a Twitter account at dark
patterns where you can share examples
that you find in the wild so some
examples that you might be familiar with
are the roach motel named after a kind
of insect trap where you can get into a
situation very easily but then it's very
hard to get out of it if you've ever
attempted to cancel a gym membership or
delete your Amazon account then you may
have found yourself a roach in a motel
another example is trick questions where
forms intentionally make it difficult to
choose the option that most use users
want for example using negation in a
non-standard way like check this box to
not receive emails from our service one
practice in our industry that's on very
shaky ethical and legal ground is growth
hacking which is a set of techniques for
achieving really rapid growth in user
base or revenue for a product and has
all the connotations you might expect
from the name hack LinkedIn was famously
very spammy when it first got started
I'd like to add you to my Professional
Network on LinkedIn became something of
a meme and this was in part because
LinkedIn made it very easy to
unintentionally send LinkedIn
invitations to every person you'd ever
emailed they ended up actually having to
pay out in a class action lawsuit
because they were sending multiple
follow-up emails when user only clicked
to send an invitation once and the
structure of their emails made it seem
like they were being sent by the user
rather than LinkedIn and the use of
these growth hacks goes back to the very
Inception of email Hotmail Market itself
in part by attacking on a signature to
the bottom of every email that said PS I
love you get your free email at Hotmail
so this seemed like it was being sent by
the actual user I grabbed a snippet from
a top 10 growth hacks article that said
that the personal sounding nature of the
message and the fact that it came from a
friend made this a very effective growth
hack but it's fundamentally deceptive to
add this to messages in such a way that
it seems personal and to not tell users
that this change is being made to the
emails that they're sending so machine
learning can actually make this problem
worse if we are optimizing short-term
metrics these growth acts and deceptive
designs can often Drive user and revenue
growth in the short term but they do
that by worsening user experience and
drawing down on Goodwill towards the
brand in a way that can erode the
long-term value of customers when we
incorporate machine learning into the
design of our products with a B testing
we have to watch out to make sure that
the the metrics that we're optimizing
don't encourage this kind of deception
so consider these two examples on the
right the top example is a very
straightforwardly implemented and direct
and easy to understand form for users to
indicate whether they want to receive
emails from the company and from its
Affiliates in example B the wording of
the first message has been changed so
that it indicates that the first hitbox
should be checked to not receive emails
while the second one should not be
ticked in order to not receive emails
and if you're a b testing these two
designs against each other and your
metric is the number of people who sign
up to receive emails then it's highly
likely that the system is going to
select example B so taking care and
setting up a b tests such that either
they're tracking longer term metrics or
things that correlate with them and that
the variant generation system that
generates all the different possible
designs can't generate any designs that
we would be unhappy with as we would
hopefully be unhappy with the deceptive
design in example B and I think it's
also important to call out that this
problem arises inside of another
alignment problem we were considering
the case where the long-term value of
customers and the company's interests
were being harmed by these deceptive
designs but unfortunately that's not
always going to be the case the private
Enterprises that build most technology
these days are able to deliver Broad
Social value to make the world a better
place as they say but the way that they
do that is generally by optimizing
metrics that are at best a very weak
proxy for that value that they're
delivering like their market
capitalization and so there's the
possibility of an alignment problem
where companies pursuing and maximizing
their own profit and success can lead to
net negative production of value and
this misalignment is something that if
you spend time at the intersection of
capital and funding leadership and
Technology development you will
encounter it so it's important to
consider these questions ahead of time
and come to your own position whether
that's trade reading this as the price
of doing business or the way the world
Works seeking ways to improve this
alignment or considering different ways
to build technology but on the shorter
term you can push for longer term
thinking within your organization to
allow for better alignment between the
metrics that you're measuring and the
goals that you're setting and between
the goals that you're setting and what
is overall good for our industry and for
the broader world and you can also learn
to recognize these user hostile design
patterns call them out when you see them
and you can advocate for a More
user-centered Design instead so to wrap
up our section on ethics for Building
Technology broadly we as an industry
should learn from other disciplines if
we want to avoid a trust crisis or if we
want to avoid the crisis getting any
worse and we can start by educating
ourselves about the common user hostile
practices in our industry and how to
avoid them now that we've covered the
kinds of ethical concerns and conflicts
that come up when Building Technology in
general let's talk about concerns that
are specific to machine learning just in
the past couple of years there have been
more and more ethical concerns raised
about the uses of machine learning and
this has gone beyond just the ethical
questions that can get raised about
other kinds of technology so we'll talk
about some of the common ethical
questions that have been raised
repeatedly over the last couple of years
and then we'll close out by talking
about what we can learn from a
particular sub-discipline of machine
learning medical machine learning so the
fundamental reason I think that ethics
is different for machine learning and
maybe more Salient is that machine
learning touches human lives more
intimately than a lot of other kinds of
technology so many machine learning
methods especially deep learning methods
make human legible data into computer
legible data so we're working on things
like computer vision on processing
natural language and humans are more
sensitive to errors in and have more
opinions about this kind of data about
images like this puppy than they do
about the other kinds of data
manipulated by computers like abstract
syntax trees so because of of this there
are more stakeholders with more concerns
that need to be traded off in machine
learning applications and then more
broadly machine learning involves being
wrong pretty much all the time there's
the famous statement that all models are
wrong though some are useful and I think
the first part applies at least
particularly strongly to machine
learning our models are statistical and
include in them Randomness the way that
we frame our problems the way that we
frame our optimization in terms of cross
entropies or divergences and Randomness
is almost always an admission of
ignorance even the quintessential
examples of Randomness like random
number generation in computers and the
flipping of a coin are things that we
know in fact are not random truly they
are in fact predictable and if we knew
the right things and had the right laws
of physics and the right computational
power then we could predict how a coin
would land we could control it we could
predict what the next number to come out
of a random number generator would be
whether it's pseudorandom or based on
some kind of Hardware Randomness and so
we're admitting a certain degree of
ignorance in our models and that means
our models are going to be wrong and
they're going to misunderstand
situations that they are put into and it
can be very upsetting and even harmful
to be misunderstood by a machine
learning model so against this backdrop
of Greater interest or higher Stakes a
number of common types of ethical
concern have coalesced in the last
couple of years and there are somewhat
established camps of answers to these
questions and you should at least know
where it is you stand on these core
questions so for four really important
questions that you should be able to
answer about about anything that you
build with machine learning are is the
model fair and what does that mean in
this situation is the system that you're
building accountable who owns the data
involved in this system and finally and
perhaps most importantly an undergirding
all of these questions is should this
system be built at all so first is the
model we're building Fair the classic
case on this comes from Criminal Justice
from the compass system for predicting
before trial whether a defendant will be
arrested again so if they're arrested
again that's just they committed a crime
during that time and so this is
assessing a certain degree of risk for
additional harm while the justice system
is deciding what to do about a previous
arrest and potential crime so the
operationalization here was a 10-point
rearrest probability based off of past
data about this person and they set a
goal from the very beginning to be less
biased than human judges so they
operationalize that by calibrating these
arrest probabilities and making sure
that if say a person received a 2 2 on
this scale they had a 20 chance of being
arrested again and then critically that
those probabilities were calibrated
across subgroups so racial bias is one
of the primary concerns around bias in
criminal justice in the United States
and so they took care to make sure that
these probabilities of rearrest were
calibrated for all racial groups the
system was deployed in it is actually
used all around the United States it's
proprietary so it's difficult to analyze
but using the Freedom of Information Act
and by colliding together a bunch of
Records some people at propublica were
able to run their own analysis of this
algorithm and they determined that
though this calibration that Compass
claimed for arrest probabilities was
there so the model was not more or less
wrong for one racial group or another
the way that the model tended to fail
was different across racial groups so
the model had more false positives for
black defendants so saying that somebody
was higher risk but then them not going
on to reoffend and had more false
negatives for white defendants so
labeling them as low risk and then them
going on to reoffend so despite North
Point the creators of compass taking
into account bias from the beginning
they ended up with an algorithm with
this undesirable property of being more
likely to effectively falsely accuse
defendants who were black than
defendants who were white this report
touched off a ton of controversy and
back and forth between propublica the
creator of the article and North Point
Craters of compass and also a bunch of
research and it turned out that some
quick algebra revealed that some form of
race-based bias is inevitable in this
setting so the things that we care about
when we're building a binary classifier
are relatively simple you can write down
all of these metrics directly so we care
about things like the false positive
rate which means we've imprisoned
somebody with no need the false negative
rate which means we missed an
opportunity to event a situation that
led to an arrest and then we also care
about the positive predictive value
which is this rearrest probability that
Compass was calibrated on so because all
of these metrics are related to each
other and related to The Joint
probability distribution of our model's
labels and the actual ground truth if
the probability of rearrest differs
across groups then we have to have that
some of these numbers are different
across groups and that is a form of
racial bias so the basic way that this
argument works just involves rearranging
these numbers and saying that if the
numbers on the left side of this
equation are different for Group 1 and
group two then it can't possibly be the
case that all three of the numbers on
the right hand side are the same for
Group 1 and group two and I'm presenting
this here as though it only impacts
these specific binary classification
metrics but there are are in fact a very
large number of definitions of fairness
which are mutually incompatible so
there's a nice a really incredible
tutorial by Arvin Narayanan who was also
the first author on the dark patterns
work on a bunch of these fairness
definitions what they mean and why
they're in commensurate so I can highly
recommend that lecture so returning to
our concrete case if the prevalence is
differ across groups then one of our
things that we're concerned with the
false positive rate the false negative
rate or the positive predictive value
will not be equal and that's something
that people can point to and say that's
unfair in the middle that positive
predictive value was equalized across
groups in compass that was what they
really wanted to make sure was equal
cross groups and because the probability
of rearrest was larger for black
defendants then either the false
positive rate had to be bigger or the
false negative rate had to be bigger for
that group and there's an analysis in
this cholachova 2017 paper that suggests
that the usual way that this will work
is that there will be a higher false
positive rate for the group with a
larger prevalence so the fact that there
will be some form of unfairness that we
can't just say oh well all these metrics
are the same across all groups and so
everything has to be fair that fact is
fixed but the impact of the unfairness
of models is not fixed the story is
often presented as oh well no matter
what the journalists would have found
something to complain about there's
always critics and so you know you don't
need to worry about fairness that much
but I think it's important to note that
the particular kind of unfairness that
came about from this model from focusing
on this positive predictive value led to
a higher false positive rate more
unnecessary imprisonment for black
defendants the false positive rate and
the positive predictive value were
equalized across groups that would have
led to a higher false negative rate for
black defendants relative to White
defendants and in the context of
American politics and concerns about
racial inequity in the criminal justice
system bias against white defendants is
not going to lead to complaints from the
same people and has a different
relationship to the historical operation
of the American justice system and so
far from this being a story about the
hopelessness of thinking about or caring
about fairness this is a story about the
necessity of confronting the trade-offs
that are inevitably going to come up so
some researchers that Google made a nice
little tool where you can try thinking
through and making these trade-offs for
yourself it's a loan decision rather
than a criminal justice decision but it
has a lot of the same properties you
have a binary classifier you have
different possible goals that you might
set either maximizing the profit of the
loaning entity or providing equal
opportunity to the two groups and it's
very helpful for building intuition on
these fairness metrics and what it means
to pay pick one over the other and these
events in this controversy kicked off a
real flurry of research on fairness and
there's now been several years of this
fairness accountability and transparity
Conference fact there's tons of work on
both algorithmic level approaches to try
and measure these fairness metrics
incorporate them into training and also
more qualitative work on designing
systems that are more transparent and
accountable so the compass example is
really important for dramatizing these
issues of fairness but I think it's very
critical for this case and for many
others to step back and ask whether this
model should be built at all so this
algorithm for scoring risk is
proprietary and uninterpretable it
doesn't give answers for why a person is
higher risk or not and because it is
closed Source there's no way to examine
it it achieves an accuracy of about 65
which is quite High given that the
marginal probability of reoffence is
much lower than 50 but it's important to
compare the baselines here pulling
together a bunch of non-experts like you
would on a jury has an accuracy of about
65 percent and creating a simple scoring
system on the basis of how old the
person is and how many prior arrests
they have also has an accuracy of around
65 and it's much easier to feel
comfortable with the system that says if
you've been arrested twice then you have
a higher risk of being arrested again
and so you'll be imprisoned before trial
then a system that just says oh well we
ran the numbers and it looks like you
have a high chance of committing a crime
but even framing this problem in terms
of who is likely to be rearrested is
already potentially a mistake so a
slightly different example of predicting
failure to appear in court was tweeted
out by Moritz heart who's one of the
main researchers in this area choosing
to try to predict who will fail to
appear in court treating this as
something that is then a fact of the
universe that this person is likely to
fail to appear in court and then
intervening on this and punishing them
for that for that fact it's important to
recognize why people fail to appear in
court in general often it's because they
don't have child care to cover for the
care of their dependence while they're
in court they don't have transportation
their work schedule is inflexible or the
core deployment schedule is inflexible
or unreasonable it'd be better to
implement steps to mitigate these issues
and reduce the number of people who are
likely to fail to appear in court for
example by making it possible to join
Court remotely that's a far better
approach for all involved than simply
getting really really good at predicting
Who currently fails to appear in court
so it's important to remember that the
things that we're measuring the things
that we're predicting are not the be-all
end-all in themselves the things that we
care about are things like an effective
and fair justice system and this comes
up perhaps most acutely in the case of
compass when we recognize that rearrest
is not the same as recidivism it's not
the same thing as committing more crimes
being rearrested requires that a police
officer believes that you committed a
crime police officers are subject effect
to their own biases and patterns of
policing result in a far higher fraction
of crimes being caught for some groups
than for others and so our real goal in
terms of fairness and criminal justice
might be around reducing those kinds of
unfair impacts and using past rearrest
data that we know has these issues to
determine who is treated more harshly by
the criminal justice system is likely to
exacerbate these issues there's also a
notion of model fairness that is broader
than just models that make decisions
about human beings so even if you're
deciding a model that works on text or
works on images you should consider
which kinds of people your model works
well for and in general representation
both on engineering and management teams
and in data sets really matters for this
kind of model fairness so it's
unfortunately still very easy to make
machine learning powered technology that
fails for minoritized groups so for
example off-the-shelf computer vision
tools will often fail on darker skin so
this is an example by Joy bull and
weenie from MIT on how a computer vision
based project that she was working on
ran into difficulties because the face
detection algorithm could not detect her
face even though it could detect the
faces of some of her friends with
lighter skin and in fact she found that
just putting on a white mask was enough
to get the computer vision model to
detect her face so this is unfortunately
not a new issue in technology it's just
a more Salient one with machine learning
so one example is that hand soap
dispensers that use infrared to
determine when to dispense soap will
often work better for lighter skin than
darker skin and issues around lighting
and vision and skin tone go back to the
foundation of Photography let alone
computer vision the design of film of
cameras and printing processes was
oriented around primarily making lighter
skin photograph well as in these
so-called Shirley cards that were used
by code DAC for calibration these
resulted in much worse experiences for
people with darker skin using these
cameras there has been a good amount of
work on this and progress since four or
five years ago one example of the kind
of tool that can help with this are
these model cards this particular format
for talking about what a model can and
cannot do that was published by a number
of researchers including Margaret
Mitchell and Timmy Gabriel it includes
explicitly considering things like on
which human subgroups of Interest many
of them minoritized identities how well
does the model perform hugging face has
good Integrations for creating these
kinds of model cards I think it's
important to note that just solving
these things by changing the data around
or by calculating demographic
information is not really an adequate
response if the CEO of Kodak or their
partner had been photographed poorly by
those cameras then there's no chance
that that issue would have been allowed
to stay for decades so when you're
looking at inviting people for talks
hiring people or joining organizations
you should try to make sure that you
have worked to reduce the bias of that
Discovery process by diversifying your
network and your input sources the
diversify Tech job board is a really
wonderful source for candidates and then
there are also professional
organizations inside of the ml World
black and Ai and women in data science
being two of the larger and more
successful ones these are great places
to get started to make the kinds of
professional connections that can
improve the representations of these
minoritized groups in the engineering
and design and product management
process where these kinds of issues
should be solved a lot of progress has
been made but these problems are still
pretty difficult to solve an unbiased
face detector might not be so
challenging but unbiased image
generation is still really difficult for
example if you make an image generation
model from internet scraped data without
any safeguards in place then if you ask
it to generate a picture of a CEO it
will generate the stereotypical CEO a
six foot or taller white man and this
applies across a wide set of jobs and
situations people can find themselves in
and this led to a lot of criticism of
early text damage generation models like
Dolly and the solution that openai opted
to this was to edit prompts that people
put in if you did not fully specify what
kind of person should be generated then
race and gender words would be added to
the prompt with weights based on the
world's population so people discovered
this somewhat embarrassingly by writing
prompts like a person holding a sign
that says or pixel art of a person
holding a text sign that says and then
seeing that the appended words were then
printed out by the model suffice it to
say that this change did not make very
many people very happy and indicates
that more work needs to be done to
de-bias image generation models at a
broader level than just fairness we can
also ask whether the system we're
building is accountable to the people
it's serving or acting upon and this is
important because some people can
consider explanation and accountability
in the face of important judgments to be
human rights this is the right to an
explanation in the European Union's
general data protection regulation gdpr
there is a subsection that mentions the
right to obtain an explanation of a
decision reached after automated
assessment and the right to challenge
that decision the legal status here is a
little bit unclear there's a nice
archive paper that talks about this a
bit about what the right to an
explanation might mean but what's more
important for our purposes is just to
know that there is an increasing chorus
of people claiming that this is indeed a
human right and it's not an entirely New
Concept and it's not even really
technology or automation specific as far
back as 1974 has been the law in the
United States that If you deny credit to
a person you must disclose the principal
reasons for denying that credit
application and in fact I found this
interesting it's expected that you
provide no more than four reasons why
you denied them credit but the general
idea that somebody as a right to know
why something happened to them in
certain cases is enshrined in some laws
so what are we supposed to do if we use
a deep neural network to decide whether
somebody should be Advanced Credit or
not so there are some off-the-shelf
methods for introspecting deep neural
networks that are all based off of input
output gradients how would changing the
pixels of this input image change the
class probabilities and the output so
this captures a kind of local
contribution but as you can see from the
small image there it doesn't produce a
very compelling map and there's no
reason to think that just changing one
pixel a tiny bit should really change
the model's output that much one
Improvement to that called Smooth grad
is to add noise to the input and then
average results kind of getting a sense
for what the gradients look like in a
general area around the input there
isn't great theory on why that should
give better explanations but people tend
to find these explanations better and
you can see in the smooth grad image on
the left there that you can pick out the
picture of a bird it seems like that is
giving a better explanation or an
explanation that we like better for why
this network is identifying that as a
picture of a bird there's a bunch of
kind of hacking methods like specific
tricks you need when you're when you're
using the relu activation there's some
methods that are better for
classification like grad cam one that is
more popular integrated gradients takes
the integral of the gradient along a
path from some baseline to the final
image and this method has a nice
interpretation in terms of Cooperative
Game Theory something called a shapley
value that quantifies how much a
particular collection of players in a
game contributed to the final reward and
adding noise to integrated gradients
tends to produce really clean
explanations that people like but
unfortunately these methods are
generally not very robust their outputs
tend to correlate pretty strongly in the
case of images with just an edge
detector there's built-in biases to
convolutional networks and the
architectures that we use that 10 and to
emphasize certain features of images
what this particular chart shows from
this archive paper by Julius adebayo
Moritz heart and others is that even as
we randomize layers in the network going
from left to right we are randomizing
starting at the top of the network and
then randomizing more layers going down
even for popular methods like integrated
gradients with smoothing or guided back
propagation we can effectively randomize
a really large fraction of the network
without changing the gross features of
the explanation and resulting in an
explanation that people would still
accept and believe even though this
network is now producing random output
so in general introspecting deep neural
networks and figuring out what's going
inside them requires something that
looks a lot more like a reverse
engineering process that's still very
much a research problem there's some
great work on distill on reverse
engineering primarily Vision networks
and then some great work from anthropic
AI recently on Transformer circuits
that's reverse engineering large Lang
language models and Chris Ola is the
researcher who's done the most work here
but it still is the sort of thing that
even getting a loose qualitative sense
for how neural networks work and what
they are doing in response to inputs is
still the type of thing that takes a
research team several years so Building
A system that can explain why it took a
particular decision is maybe not
currently possible with deep neural
networks but that doesn't mean that the
systems that we build with them have to
be unaccountable if somebody dislikes
the decision that they get and the
explanation that we give is well the
neural network said you shouldn't get a
loan and they challenge that it might be
time to bring in a human in the loop to
make that decision and building that in
to the system so that it's an expected
mode of operation and is considered an
important part of the feedback and the
operation of the system is key to
building an accountable system so this
book automating inequality by Virginia
Eubanks talks a little bit about the
ways in which Technical Systems as their
build today are very prone to this
unaccountability where the people who
are Indian most impacted by these
systems some of the most critical
stakeholders for these systems for
example recipients of government
assistance are unable to have their
voices and their needs heard and taken
into account in the operation of a
system so this is perhaps the point at
which you should ask when building a
system with machine learning whether
this should be built at all and
particular to ask who benefits and who
is harmed by automating this task in
addition to concerns around the behavior
of models increasing concern has been
pointed towards data and in particular
who owns and who has rights to the data
involved in the creation of machine
Learning Systems it's important to
remember that the training data that we
use for our machine learning algorithms
is almost always generated by humans and
they generally feel some ownership over
that data and we end up behaving a
little bit like this comic on the right
where they hand us some data that they
made and then we say oh this is ours now
I made this and in particular the large
data sets you train the really large
models that are pushing the frontiers of
what is possible with machine learning
are produced by crawling the Internet by
searching over all the images all the
text posted on the internet and pulling
large fractions of it down and many
people are not aware that this is
possible let alone legal and so to some
extent any consent that they gave to
their data being used was not informed
and then additionally as technology has
changed in the last decade and machine
learning has gotten better what can be
done with data has changed somebody
uploading their art a decade ago
certainly did not have on their radar
the idea that they were giving consent
to that art being used to create an
algorithm that can mimic its style and
you can in fact check whether an image
of interest to you has been used to
train one of the large text image models
specifically this have I been
trained.com website will search through
the Leon data set that is used to train
the stable diffusion model for images
that you upload so you can look to see
if any pictures of you were incorporated
into the data set and this goes further
than just pictures that people might
rather not have used in this way to
actual data that has somehow been
obtained illegally there's an Arts
technical article a particular artist
who was interested in this found that
some of their medical photos which they
did not consent to have uploaded to the
internet somehow found their way into
the lay on data set and so cleaning
large web scraped data sets from this
kind of illegally obtained data is
definitely going to be important as more
attention is paid to these models as
they are product eyes and monetized and
more on people's radar even for data
that is obtained legally saying well
technically you did agree to this does
not generally satisfy people remember
the Facebook emotion research study
technically some reading of the Facebook
user data policy did support the way
that they were running their experiment
but many users disagreed many artists
feel that creating an art generation
tool that threatens their livelihoods
and copies art down to the point of even
faking watermarks and logos on images
when told to recreate the style of an
artist is an ethical use of that data
and it certainly is the case that
creating a sort of parrot that can mimic
somebody is something that a lot of
people find concerning dealing with
these issues around data governance is
likely to be a new frontier imagine of
stable diffusion has said that he's
partnering with people to create
mechanisms for artists to opt in or opt
out of being included in training data
sets for future versions of stable
diffusion I found that noteworthy
because mostacc has been very vocal in
his defense of image generation
technology and of what it can be used
for but even he is interested in
adjusting the way data is used there's
also been work from Tech forward artists
like Holly Hunter who was involved in
the creation of have I been trained
around trying to incorporate AI systems
into art in a way that empowers artists
and compensates them rather than
immiserating them just as we can create
cards for models we can also create
cards for data sets that describe how
they were curated what the sources were
and any other potential issues with the
data and perhaps in the future even how
to opt out of or be removed from a data
set so this is an example from a hugging
face as with model cards there's lots of
good examples of data set cards on
hugging face there's also a nice
checklist the Dion ethics checklist that
is mostly focused around data ethics but
covers a lot of other ground they also
have this nice list of examples for each
question in their checklist of cases
where people have run into ethical or
legal trouble by building an ml project
that didn't satisfy a particular
checklist item running underneath all of
this has been this final most important
question of whether this system should
be built at all one particular use case
that very frequently elicits this
question is building ml-powered Weaponry
ml powered Weaponry is already here it's
already starting to be deployed in the
world there are some remote controlled
weapons that use computer vision for
targeting deployed by the Israeli
military in the West Bank using this
smart shooter technology that's designed
to in principle take normal weapons and
add computer vision based targeting to
them to make them into smart weapons
right now this deployed system shown on
the left uses only sponge tipped bullets
which are designed to be less lethal but
they can still cause serious injury and
according to the deployers in the pilot
stage so it's a little unclear to what
extent autonomous Weaponry is already
here and being used because the
definition is a little bit blurry so for
example the hayrop Drone shown in the
top left is a loitering munition a type
of drone that can fly around hold its
position for a while and then
automatically destroy any radar system
that locks onto it this type of drone
was used in the nagorno-karabakh war
between Armenia and Azerbaijan in 2021
but there's also older autonomous weapon
systems the Phalanx c-whiz is designed
to automatically fire at Targets moving
towards Naval vessels at very very high
velocities so these are velocities
they're usually only achieved by rocket
Munitions not by manned craft and that
system's been used since at least the
first Gulf War in 1991. there was an
analysis in 2017 by The Economist to try
and look for how many systems with
automated targeting there were and in
particular how many of them could engage
with targets without involving humans at
all so that would be the last section of
human out of the loop systems but given
the general level of secrecy in some
cases and hype and others around
military technology it can be difficult
to get a very clear sense and the
blurriness of this definition has led
some to say that autonomous weapons are
actually at least 100 years old for
example anti-personnel mines that were
used starting in the 30s and in World
War II attempts to you detect whether a
person has come close to them and then
explode and in some sense that is an
autonomous weapon and if we broaden our
definition that far then maybe lots of
different kinds of traps are some form
of autonomous weapon but just because
these weapons already exist and maybe
even have been around for a century does
not mean that designing ml-powered
weapons is ethical anti-personnel mines
in fact are the subject of a mind Ban
Treaty that a very large number of
countries have signed unfortunately not
some of the countries with the largest
militaries in the world but that at
least suggests that for one type of
autonomous weapon that has caused a
tremendous amount of collateral damage
there's interest in Banning them and so
perhaps rather than building these
autonomous weapons so we can then ban
them it would be better if we just
didn't build them at all so the campaign
to stop Killer Robots is a group to look
into if this is something that's
interesting to you it brings us to the
end of our tour of the four common
questions that people raise around the
ethics of building an ml system I've
provided some of my answers to these
questions and some of the common answers
to these questions but you should have
thoughtful answers to these for the
individual projects that you work on
first is the model fair I think it's
generally possible but it requires
trade-offs is the system accountable I
think it's pretty challenging to make
interpretable deep Learning Systems
where interpretability allows an
explanation for why a decision was made
but making a system that's accountable
where answers can be changed in response
to user feedback or perhaps user lawsuit
is possible you'll definitely want to
answer the question of who owns the data
up front and be on the lookout for
changes especially to these large-scale
internet scraped data sets and then
lastly should this be built at all
you'll want to ask this repeatedly
throughout the life cycle of the
technology I wanted to close this
section by talking about just how much
the machine learning world can learn
from medicine and from applications of
machine learning to medical problems
this is a field I've had a chance to
work in and I've seen some of the best
work on building with ML responsibly
come from this field and fundamentally
it's because of a mismatch between
machine learning and medicine that
impedance mismatch has led to a ton of
learning so first we'll talk about the
Fiasco that was machine learning and the
covid-19 pandemic then briefly consider
why medicine would have this big of a
mismatch with machine learning and what
the benefits of examining it closer
might be and then lastly we'll talk
about some concrete research on auditing
and Frameworks for building with ML that
have come out of medicine first
something that should be scary and
embarrassing for people in machine
learning medical researchers found that
almost all machine learning research on
covid-19 was effectively useless this is
in the context of a biomedical response
to covid-19 that was an absolute Triumph
in the first year vaccinations prevented
some tens of millions of deaths these
vaccines were designed based on novel
Technologies like lipid nanoparticles
for delivering mRNA and even more
traditional techniques like small
molecule Therapeutics for example
paxilavid the quality of research that
was done was extremely high so on the
right we have an inferred 3D structure
for a coronavirus protein in complex
with the primary effective molecule in
paxilavid allowing for a mechanistic
understanding of how this drug was
working at the atomic level and at this
crucial time machine learning did not
really acquit itself well so there were
two reviews one in bmj and one in nature
that reviewed a large set of prediction
models for covid-19 either prognosis or
diagnosis primarily prognosis in the
case of the Winans at all paper in bmj
or diagnosis on the basis of chest
x-rays and CT scans and both of these
reviews found that almost all of the
papers were insufficiently documented
did not follow best practices for
developing models and did not have
sufficient external validation testing
on external data to justify any wider
use of these models even though many of
them were provided as software or apis
ready to be used in a clinical setting
so the depth of the errors here is
really very sobering a full quarter of
the papers analyzed in the Roberts at
all review used a pneumonia data set as
a control group so the idea was we don't
want our model just to detect whether
people are sick or not just having
having coveted patients and healthy
patients might cause models that detect
all pneumonias as covid so let's
incorporate this pneumonia data set but
they failed to mention and perhaps
failed to notice that the pneumonia data
set was all children all pediatric
patients so the models that they were
training were very likely just detecting
children versus adults because that
would give them perfect performance on
Pneumonia versus covid on that data set
so it's a pretty egregious error of
modeling and data set construction
alongside bunch of other more subtle
errors around proper validation and
reporting of models and methods so I
think one reason for the substantial
difference in responses here is that
medicine both in practice and in
research has a very strong professional
culture of Ethics that equips it to
handle very very serious and difficult
problems at least in the United States
medical doctors still take the
Hippocratic Oath parts of which date
back all the way to Hippocrates one of
the founding fathers of Greek medicine
and one of the core precepts of that
oath is to do no harm meanwhile one of
the core precepts of the Contemporary
tech industry represented here by this
ml generated Greek bust of Mark
Zuckerberg is to move fast and break
things with the implication that
breaking things is not so bad and well
that's probably the right approach for
building lots of kinds of web
applications and other software when
this culture gets applied to things like
medicine the results can be really ugly
one particularly striking example of
this was when a retinal implant that was
used to restore sight to some blind
people was deprecated by the vendor and
so stopped working and there was no
recourse for these patients because
there is no other organization capable
of maintaining these devices the news
here is not all bad for machine learning
there are researchers who are working at
the intersection of medicine and machine
learning and developing and proposing
solutions to some of these issues that I
think might have broad applicability on
building responsibly with machine
learning first the clinical trial
standards that are used for other
medical devices and for pharmaceuticals
have been extended to machine learning
the spirit standard for Designing
clinical trials and the consort standard
for reporting results of clinical trials
these have both been extended to include
ml with Spirit Ai and consort AI two
Links at the bottom of this slide for
the details on the contents of both of
those standards one thing I wanted to
highlight here was the process by which
these standards were created and which
is reported in those research articles
which included an international survey
with over a hundred participants and
then a conference with 30 participants
to come up with a final checklist and
then a pilot use of it to determine how
well it worked so the standard for
producing standards in medicine is also
quite high and something we could very
much learn from in machine learning so
because of that work and because people
have pointed out these concerns progress
is being made on doing better work in
machine learning for medicine this
recent paper in the Journal of the
American Medical Association does a
review of clinical trials involving
machine learning and finds that for many
of the components of these clinical
trial standards compliance and quality
is very high incorporating clinical
context state very clearly how the
method will contribute to clinical care
but there are definitely some places
with poor compliance for example
interestingly enough very few trials
reported how low quality data was
handled how data was assessed for
quality and and how cases of poor
quality data should be handled I think
that's also something that the broader
machine learning world could do a better
job on and then also analysis of errors
that models made which also shows up in
medical research and clinical trials as
analysis of Adverse Events this kind of
error analysis was not commonly done and
this is something that in talking about
testing and troubleshooting and in
talking about model monitoring and
continual learning we've tried to
emphasize the importance of this kind of
error analysis for building with ML
there's also this really gorgeous pair
of papers by Lauren Oakton Raynor and
others in the Lancet that both developed
and applied this algorithmic auditing
framework for medical ml so this is
something that is probably easier to
incorporate into other ml workflows than
is a full-on clinical trial approach but
still has some of the same rigor
incorporates checklists and tasks and
defined artifacts that highlight what
the problems are and what needs to be
tracked and shared while building a
machine Learning System one particular
component that I wanted to highlight and
is here indicated in blue is that
there's a big emphasis on failure modes
and error analysis and what they call
adversarial testing which is coming up
with different kinds of inputs to put
into the model to see how it performs so
sort of like a behavioral check on the
model these are all things that we've
emphasized as part of how to build a
model well there's lots of other
components of this audit that the
broader ml Community would do well to
incorporate into their work there's a
ton of really great work being done a
lot of these papers are just within the
last three or six months so I think it's
a pretty good idea to keep your finger
on the pulse here so to speak in medical
ml the Stanford in Institute for AI and
medicine has a regular panel that gets
posted on YouTube they also share a lot
of great other kinds of content via
Twitter and then a lot of the
researchers who did some of the work
that I shared Lauren Oakton Raynor
Benjamin Khan are also active on Twitter
along with other folks who've done great
work that I didn't get time to talk
about like Judy chichoya and Matt
Lundgren closing out this section like
medicine machine learning can be very
intimately intertwined with people's
lives and so ethics is really really
Salient perhaps the most important
ethical question to ask ourselves over
and over again is should this system be
built at all what are the implications
of building the system of automating
this task or this work and it seems
clear that if we don't regulate
ourselves we will end up being regulated
and so we should learn from older
Industries like medicine rather than
just assuming we can disrupt our way
through so as our final section I want
to talk about the ethics of artificial
intelligence this is clearly a frontier
both for the field of Ethics trying to
think through these problems and for the
technology communities that are building
this I think that right now false claims
and hype around artificial intelligence
are the most pressing concern but we
shouldn't sleep on some of the major
ethical issues that are potentially
oncoming with AI so right now claims and
Hyperbole and hype around artificial
intelligence are outpacing capabilities
even though those capabilities are also
growing fast and this risks a kind of
blowback so one way to summarize this is
say that if you call something autopilot
people are going to treat it like
autopilot and then be upset or worse
when that's not the case so famously
there is an incident where somebody who
believed that Tesla is lean and braking
assistant system autopilot was really
full self-driving was killed in a car
crash in this gap between what people
expect out of ml systems and what they
actually get is something that Josh
talked about in the project management
lecture so this is something that we're
already having to incorporate into our
engineering and our product design that
people are overselling the capacities of
ml systems in a way that gives users a
bad idea of what is possible and this
problem is very widespread even large
and mature organizations like IBM can
create products like Watson which was
the capable question and answering
system and then sell it as artificial
intelligence and try to revolutionize or
disrupt Fields like medicine and then
end up falling far short of these
extremely lofty goals they've set
themselves and along the way they get at
least the beginning journalistic
coverage with pictures of robot hands
reaching out to grab balls of light or
brains inside computers or computers
inside brains so not only do companies
oversell what their technology can do
but these overstatements are repeated or
Amplified by traditional and social
media and this problem even extends to
Academia there is a Infamous now case
where Japan in 2017 said that
Radiologists at that point were like
Wiley Coyote already over the edge of
the cliff and haven't realized that
there's no ground underneath them and
that people should stop training
Radiologists now because within five
years AKA now deep learning is going to
be better than Radiologists some of the
work in the intersection of medicine in
ml that I presented was done by people
who were in their Radiology training at
the time around the time this statement
was made and were lucky that they
continued training as Radiologists while
also gaining ml expertise so that they
could do the slow hard work of bringing
deep learning and machine learning into
Radiology this overall problem of
overselling artificial intelligence you
could call AI snake oil so that's the
name of an upcoming book and a new sub
stack by Arvin Narayanan are now very
good friend and so this refers not just
to people overselling the capabilities
of large language models or predicting
that we'll have artificial intelligence
by Christmas but people who use this
General Aura of hypanic segment around
artificial intelligence to sell shoddy
technology an example from this really
great set of slides linked here the tool
Elevate that claims to be able to assess
personality and job suitability from a
30 second video including identifying
whether the person in the video is a
change agent or not so the call here is
to separate out the actual places where
there's been rapid Improvement in what's
possible with machine learning for
example computer perception identifying
the contents of images face recognition
Orion in here even includes medical
diagnosis from scans from places where
there's not been as much progress and so
the split that he proposes that I think
is helpful is that most things that
involve some form of human judgment like
determining whether something is hate
speech or what grade an essay should
receive these are on the borderline most
forms of prediction especially around
what he calls social outcomes so things
like policing jobs Child Development
these are places where there has not
been substantial progress and where the
risk of somebody essentially riding the
coattails of gpt3 with some technique
that doesn't perform any better than
linear regression is at its highest so
we don't have artificial intelligence
yet but if we do synthesize intelligent
agents a lot of thorny ethical questions
are going to immediately arise so it's
probably a good idea as a field and as
individuals for us to think a little bit
about these ahead of time so there's
broad agreement that creating sentient
intelligent beings would have ethical
implications just this past summer
Google engineer Blake Lemoine became
convinced that a large language model
built by Google Lambda was in fact
conscious and almost everyone agrees
that that's not the case for these large
language models but there's pretty big
disagreement on how far away we are and
perhaps most importantly this concern
did cause a pretty big reaction both
inside the field and in the popular
press in my view it's a bit unfortunate
that this conversation was started so
early because it's so easy to dismiss
this claim if it happens too many more
times we might end up inured to these
kinds of conversations in a boy who
cried AI type situation there's also a
different set of concerns around what
might happen with the creation of a
self-improving artificial intelligence
so there's already some hints in this
direction for one the latest Nvidia GPU
architecture Hopper incorporates a very
large number of AI design circuits
pictured here on the left the quality of
the AI design circuits are superior this
is also something that's been reported
by the folks working on tpus at Google
there's also cases in which large
language models can be used to build
better models for example large language
models can teach themselves to program
better and large language models can
also use large language models at least
as well as humans this suggests the
possibility of virtuous Cycles in
machine learning capabilities and
machine intelligence and failing to
pursue this kind of very powerful
technology comes with a very substantial
opportunity cost this is something
that's argued by the philosopher Nick
Bostrom in a famous paper called
astronomical waste that points out just
given the size of the universe the
amount of resources and the amount of
time it will be around there's a huge
cost in terms of potential good
potential lives worth living that we
leave on the table if we do not develop
the Necessary Technology quickly but the
primary lesson that's drawn in this
paper is actually not that technology
should be developed as quickly as
possible but rather that it should be
developed as safely as possible which is
to say that the probability that this
imagined Galaxy or Universe spanning
Utopia comes into being that probability
should be maximized and so this concern
around safety originating the work of
Bostrom and others has become a central
concern for people thinking about the
ethical implications of artificial
intelligence and so the concerns around
self-improving intelligent systems that
could end up being more intelligent than
humans are nicely summarized in the
parable of the paperclip maximizer also
from Bostrom at least popularized in the
book super intelligence so the idea here
is a classic example of this proxy
problem in alignment so we design an
artificial intelligence system for
building paper clips so it's designed to
make sure that the paper clip producing
component of our economy runs as
effectively as possible produces as many
paper clips as it can and we incorporate
self-improvement into it so that it
becomes smarter and more capable over
time at first it improves human utility
as it introduces better industrial
processes for paper clips but as it
becomes more intelligent perhaps it
finds a way to manipulate the legal
system and manipulate politics to
introduce a more favorable tax code for
pay-per-clip related Industries and that
starts to hurt overall human utility uh
even as the number of paper clips
created and the capacity of the
paperclip maximizer increases and of
course at the point when we have
mandatory national service in the
paperclip mines or that all matter in
the universe is converted to paper clips
we've pretty clearly decreased human
utility as this paperclip maximizer has
maximized its objective and increased
its own capacity so this still feels
fairly far away and a lot of the
speculations feel a lot more like
science fiction than science fact but
the stakes here are high enough that it
is certainly worth having some people
thinking about and working on it and
many of the techniques can be applied to
controlled and responsible deployment of
less capable ml systems as a small aside
these ideas around existential risk and
super intelligences are often associated
with the effective altruism Community
which is concerned with the best ways to
do the most good both with what you do
with your career one of the focuses is
the 80 000 hours organization and also
through charitable donations as a way to
by donating to the highest impact
Charities and non-profits have the
largest positive impact on the world so
there's a lot of very interesting ideas
coming out of this community and it's
particularly appealing to a lot of folks
who work in technology and especially in
machine learning so it's worth checking
out so that brings us to the end of our
planned agenda here after giving some
context around what our approach to
Ethics in this lecture would look like
we talked about ethical concerns in
three different fields first past and
immediate concerns around the ethical
development of Technology then up and
coming and near future concerns around
building ethically with machine learning
and then finally a taste of the ethical
concerns we might face in a future where
machine learning gives way to artificial
intelligence with a reminder that we
should make sure not to oversell our
progress on that front so I got to the
end of these slides and realized that
this was the end of the course and felt
that I couldn't leave it on uh dower and
sad note of unusable medical algorithms
and existential risk from Super
intelligences so I wanted to close out
with a bit of a more positive note on
the things that we can do so I think the
first and most obvious step is education
a lot of these ideas around ethics are
unfamiliar to people with a technical
background there's a lot of great longer
form content that captures a lot of
these ideas and can help you build your
own knowledge of the history and context
and eventually your own opinions on
these topics I can highly recommend each
of these books the alignment problem is
a great place to get started it focuses
pretty tightly on ML ethics and AI
ethics it covers a lot of recent
research and is very easily digestible
for an ml audience you might also want
to consider some of these books around
more Tech ethics like weapons of math
destruction by Kathy O'Neill and
automating inequality by Virginia
Eubanks from there you can prioritize
things that you want to act on make your
own two by two around things that have
impact now and can have very high impact
for me I think that's things around
deceptive design and dark patterns and
around AI snake oil then there's also
places where acting in the future might
be very important and high impact for me
I think that's things around ml Weaponry
behind my head is existential risk from
Super intelligences on super high impact
but something that we can't act on right
now and then all the things in between
you can create your own two by two on
these and then search around for
organizations communities and people
working on these problems to align
yourself with and by way of a final
goodbye as we're ending this class I
want to call out that a lot of the
discussion of Ethics in this lecture was
very negative because of the framing
around cases where people raised ethical
concerns but ethics is not and cannot be
purely negative about avoiding doing bad
things the work that we do in Building
Technology with machine learning can do
good in the world not just avoid doing
harm we can reduce suffering so this
diagram here from a neuroscience from a
brain machine interface paper from 2012
is what got me into the field of machine
learning in the first place it shows a
tetraplegic woman who has learned to
control a robot arm using only other
thoughts by means of an electrode
attached to her head and while the
technical achievements in this paper
were certainly very impressive the thing
that made the strongest impression on me
reading this paper in college was the
smile on the woman's face in the final
panel if you've experienced this kind of
limit Mobility either yourself or in
someone close to you then you know that
the joy even from something as simple as
being able to feed yourself is very real
we can also do good by increasing Joy
not just reducing suffering despite the
concerns that we talked about with text
to image models there they're clearly
being used to create Beauty and Joy or
as Ted Underwood a digital Humanity
scholar put it to explore a dimension of
human culture that was accidentally
created across the last five thousand
years of captioning that's beautiful and
it's something we should hold on to
that's not to say that this happens
automatically by Building Technology the
world automatically becomes better but
leading organizations in our field are
making proactive statements on this
openai around long term safely around
long-term safety and Broad distribution
of the benefits of machine learning and
artificial intelligence research Deep
Mind stating which Technologies they
won't pursue and making a clear
statement of a gold a broadly benefit
Humanity the final bit of really great
news that I have is that the tools for
building ml well that you've learned
throughout this class align very well
with building ml for good so we saw it
with the medical machine learning around
failure analysis and we can also see it
in the principles for for responsible
development from these leading
organizations Deep Mind mentioning
accountability to people and Gathering
feedback Google AI mentioning it as well
and if you look closely at Google ai's
list of recommended practices for
responsible AI use multiple metrics to
assess training and monitoring
understand limitations use tests
directly examine raw data Monitor and
update your system after deployment
these are exactly the same principles
that we've been emphasizing in this
course around building ml powered
products the right way these techniques
will also help you build machine
learning that does what's right and so
on that note I want to thank you for
your time and your interest in this
course
and I wish you the best of luck as you
go out to build with ML